The adventure takes off when toys come to life!
Toy Story is a family, comedy, animation film directed by John Lasseter.
Led by Woody, Andy's toys live happily in his room until Andy's
birthday brings Buzz Lightyear onto the scene.
Afraid of losing his place in Andy's heart, Woody plots against Buzz.
But when circumstances separate Buzz and Woody from their owner, the
duo eventually learns to put aside their differences.
Woody (voice), played by Tom Hanks.
Buzz Lightyear (voice), played by Tim Allen.
Mr. Potato Head (voice), played by Don Rickles.
Slinky Dog (voice), played by Jim Varney.
Rex (voice), played by Wallace Shawn.
Hamm (voice), played by John Ratzenberger.
Toy Story is a 1995 American animated adventure comedy film produced
by Pixar Animation Studios for Walt Disney Pictures.
It is the first installment in the Toy Story franchise and the first entirely
computer-animated feature film, as well as the first feature film from Pixar.
The film was directed by John Lasseter, written by Joss Whedon, Andrew Stanton, Joel Cohen, and Alec Sokolow based on a story by Lasseter, Stanton, Pete Docter, and Joe Ranft,
produced by Bonnie Arnold and Ralph Guggenheim, and features the voices of Tom Hanks, Tim Allen, Annie Potts, John Ratzenberger, Don Rickles, Wallace Shawn, and Jim Varney.
Taking place in a world where toys come to life when humans are not present, Toy Story follows an old-fashioned pullstring cowboy doll named Woody Pride, referred to simply by
his first name, and a modern space cadet action figure, Buzz Lightyear, as Woody develops jealousy towards Buzz when he becomes their owner Andy's favorite toy.
Following the success of the 1988 short film Tin Toy, Pixar was approached by Disney to produce
a computer-animated feature film that was told from a small toy's perspective.
Lasseter, Stanton, and Docter wrote early story treatments, which were
rejected by Disney, who wanted the film's tone to be "edgier".
After several disastrous story reels, production was halted and the script was rewritten to better reflect
the tone and theme Pixar desired: "toys deeply want children to play with them, and ...
this desire drives their hopes, fears, and actions".
The studio, then consisting of a relatively small number of employees,
produced Toy Story under minor financial constraints.
Toy Story premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Los Angeles on November 19, 1995, and
was released in theaters in North America three days later on November 22.
It was the highest-grossing film during its opening weekend, eventually grossing over
$363 million worldwide, making it the second highest-grossing film of 1995.
The film received critical acclaim, with praise directed towards the technical innovation of the animation, script, Randy Newman's score, appeal to all age
groups, and voice performances (particularly Hanks and Allen), and holds a 100% approval rating on film aggregation website Rotten Tomatoes.
The film is frequently lauded as one of the best animated films ever made and, due to its status as the first
computer-animated film, one of the most important films in the medium's history and film at large.
The film received three Academy Award nominations—Best Original Screenplay (the first animated film to be nominated for the award), Best Original Song for
"You've Got a Friend in Me", and Best Original Score—in addition to being honored with a non-competitive Special Achievement Academy Award.
In 2005, Toy Story was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of Congress as being
"culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant", one of nine films designated in its first year of eligibility.
The success of Toy Story launched a multimedia franchise, spawning four sequels beginning with
Toy Story 2 (1999); a spin-off film Lightyear (2022); and numerous short films.
The film has had several theatrical re-releases, including a 3D re-release in 2009 as part of a
double feature with the second film and a 30th anniversary re-release in 2025.
The film explores themes of rescue, friendship, mission, jealousy, villain.
The tone is lighthearted.